{"tossups": [{"question": "A holder of this position, Philip Snowden, responded to the start of the Great Depression by investigating government cutbacks in the May Report. In 1911, the holder of this position attacked German aggression in the Mediterranean in a Mansion House Speech. David Lloyd George held this position for seven years beginning in 1908, during which time he issued the People\u2019s Budget. For the point, name this position responsible for managing the British treasury.", "answer": "<b> Chancellor</b> of the Exchequer (accept<b> Exchequer</b>; accept<b> Chancellor</b> (and Under-Treasurer) of Her Majesty\u2019s Exchequer; do not accept or prompt on Lord Chancellor)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A group of scientists in this country formed the VfR, a \u201cSociety for Space Travel,\u201d after consulting on the film<em> The Woman in the Moon</em>. The Farm Hill transcripts detail conversations between ten nuclear physicists from this country who were detained in England. This country\u2019s Uranium Club included a man who stated an Uncertainty Principle. Werner Heisenberg was born in, for the point, what country in which Philip Lenard led the Aryan Physics movement?", "answer": "Nazi<b> Germany</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "At a battle fought off the shores of this country, Admiral Halsey aggressively maneuvered the U.S. Third Fleet north, earning that battle the nickname \u201cBull\u2019s Run.\u201d Masaharu Homma was executed for war crimes he committed in this country, where he forced a group of POWs to trek sixty miles to Camp O\u2019Donnell. The Battle of Leyte Gulf was fought near this country, where Japanese forces carried out the Bataan Death March. For the point, name this Asian country to which Douglas MacArthur vowed to return.", "answer": "the<b> Philippines</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A character in this novel steals a cross and a watch from a dead French officer who turns out to still be alive, and who mistakenly thanks the thief for saving his life. This novel\u2019s lengthy digressions include an analysis of the Battle of Waterloo from the French perspective and an account of Paris\u2019s sewer system, which is navigated when Marius Pontmercy is carried to safety from a barricade during the 1832 June Rebellion. For the point, name this novel about Inspector Javert [zha-vair] and Jean Valjean, written by Victor Hugo.", "answer": "Les<b> Mis\u00b4erables</b> (do not accept or prompt on \u201cLes Miz\u201d)", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "A ruler of this dynasty tried to legitimize his rule by forcing dissident ministers to recite poetry but failed to so and thus executed those \u201csix martyred ministers.\u201d This dynasty launched an expedition against the Tsushima Islands and established a \u201cHall of the Worthies\u201d for scholars. Taejo founded this dynasty, which was aided in fighting off a Japanese invasion by Yi Sun-Sin, after which it became isolationist and was known as a \u201chermit kingdom.\u201d Sejong the Great once led, for the point, what Korean dynasty that ruled from the fall of Goryeo to the early 20th century?", "answer": "<b> Joseon</b> Dynasty (or<b> Choson</b> Dynasty)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Joseph Galloway presented a Plan of Union to this body that was firmly rejected. This body, which endorsed the Suffolk Resolves as a move of solidarity, was presided over by Henry Middleton after the departure of its original president, Peyton Randolph. In its Declaration and Resolves, this body requested that Committees of Safety boycott British trade. The Intolerable Acts were the impetus for, for the point, what 1774 meeting between delegates of the Thirteen Colonies that failed to stave off the Revolutionary War?", "answer": "<b> First Continental Congress</b> (prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This group orchestrated the murder of the university student Benno Ohnesorg in an attempt to sow chaos in an enemy country. This organization quietly provided technical and financial support to the Red Army Faction, and perfected its own gaslighting technique called<em> zersetzung</em>. Prominent members of this organization included longtime leader Erich Mielke and a man who successfully led the infiltration of Willy Brandt\u2019s cabinet, Markus Wolf. For the point, name this official intelligence service of East Germany.", "answer": "<b> Stasi</b> (accept<b> Ministry for State Security</b> or<b> State Security Service</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In 2010, while working at this university, Reinhard and Rogoff wrote the austerity-promoting paper\u201cGrowth in a Time of Debt.\u201d A seminar co-taught by Michael Walzer and Robert Nozick at this university was titled \u201cCapitalism and Socialism\u201d and resulted in the publication of<em> Anarchy, State, and Utopia</em>. This university\u2019s popular \u201cJustice\u201d course is taught by Michael Sandel and discusses one of this school\u2019s longest serving philosophy professors, John Rawls. For the point, name this Ivy League university once headed by Lawrence Summers, located in Cambridge, Massachusetts.", "answer": "<b> Harvard</b> University", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {"question": "A chronicle that describes this battle was composed 22 years later by Isidore of Beja. In the leadup to this battle, Odo\u2019s forces were soundly defeated near Bordeaux in the Battle of the River Garonne. In this battle, Abdul Rahman was killed during the losing side\u2019s retreat, in which they were pursued by Frankish infantry. For the point, name this 8th century battle in which Charles Martel\u2019s army defeated an Umayyad invasion of France.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Tours</b> (accept Battle of<b> Poitiers</b>; accept Battle of the<b> Palace of the Martyrs</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man was supported by William Wade Dudley, who controversially suggested bribing voters in\u201cblocks of five.\u201d The Dependent and Disability Pension act was championed by this Ohio Congressman, who later signed it into law. Near the end of his administration, this man\u2019s plan to annex Hawaii was blocked by the Senate. The Billion Dollar Congress supported this President and passed the harsh McKinley tariff. For the point, name this president who both succeeded and preceded Grover Cleveland.", "answer": "<b> B</b>enjamin<b> Harrison</b> (prompt on Harrison)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "According to legend, the four sons of Aymon fled to this region on the magical river-jumping horse Bayard. Charlemagne is said to have dreamed of this region the night before the disaster at Roncevaux Pass. The Dinant region in this forest was targeted by Heinz Guderian at the end of the Phony War, since it was undefended by the Maginot Line. This forest was also exploited by panzers in the Battle of the Bulge. For the point, name this largely Belgian forest that provided a route for the Nazi invasion of France.", "answer": "<b> Ardennes</b> Forest (prompt on Belgium and/or Wallonia before \u201cforest\u201d is said)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Nuon Chea, who briefly interrupted this man\u2019s term as Prime Minister, was this man\u2019s second-in-command and known as\u201cBrother Number Two.\u201d For the point, name this first prime minister of Democratic Kampuchea, the leader of the Khmer Rouge.", "answer": "<b> Pol Pot</b> (accept Saloth<b> Sar</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A spy working for this country gained information about American troops by romancing US Senator Henry Wilson. This country utilized the spies Rose Greenhow and Belle Boyd. Because this country\u2019s only major arms manufacturer was the Tredegar Iron Works, it employed blockade runners to bypass ships enforcing the Anaconda Plan. For the point, name this country whose Secretary of State, Judah Benjamin, managed its covert operations from its capital of Richmond, Virginia.", "answer": "<b> Confederate</b> States of America (accept<b> CSA</b>; accept<b> Confederacy</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A popular portrait of this man in a blue robe and light blue tights was painted by Hyacinthe Rigaud [ree-GOH]. Andre-Charles Boulle\u2019s inlay work was prized by this king\u2019s court. This king commissioned the muralist Charles Le Brun to paint scenes of embassies to his court on the ceiling of the Hall of Mirrors. This man commissioned the architect Louis Le Vau to oversee the expansion of the gardens and Palace of Versailles. For the point, name this Bourbon \u201cSun King.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Louis XIV</b> [14]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This politician successfully ordered Sir John Napier to rescue Protestant hostages taken by Tewodros II of Ethiopia. Under his tenure, this man\u2019s country suffered a severe defeat in the Battle of Isandlwana by Zulu warriors. This man represented his country with Lord Salisbury at the Congress of Berlin, and he won acclaim for purchasing majority shares in the Suez Canal for his nation. Queen Victoria was a fervent supporter of, for the point, what British prime minister, a rival of William Gladstone?", "answer": "Benjamin<b> Disraeli</b>, 1st Earl of Beaconfield", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A resident of this city named Joshua Norton issued his own money and declared himself Emperor of the United States. Daniel Burnham proposed a Haussmann-style reconstruction of this city, where Levi Strauss founded his jeans company following the 1849 California Gold Rush. Alcatraz Prison lies in a bay north of, for the point, what California city that was struck by a 1906 earthquake and fire?", "answer": "<b> San Francisco</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During one of these events, Richard Temple opened work camps and was criticized for \u201cteaching the natives that it is the duty of the government to keep them alive.\u201d Another of these events that took place in India in the late 18th century was nicknamed for the skulls of its victims. One of these events, known locally as An Gortha Mor, was caused in part by overreliance on the Lumper variety of a certain crop. For the point, name these events, one of which caused thousands of refugees to flee Ireland in the 1840s and was caused by a potato-killing blight.", "answer": "<b> famine</b>s (accept Bengal<b> famine</b>; accept Doji bara<b> famine</b> or skull<b> famine</b>; accept Irish potato<b> famine</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Prior to its foundation, the residents of this city journeyed from the Place of Herons to Grasshopper Hill, where they got in trouble for flaying a princess of the Culhua people. This city\u2019s sacred precinct was centered around a double temple to deities of war and rain, the Templo Mayor. This city was founded in a marsh at the spot where an eagle atop a cactus was eating a snake, supposedly a sign sent by Huitzilopotchli [h\u2019weet-zee-loh-pock-t\u2019lee]. For the point, name this Aztec capital city.", "answer": "<b> Tenochtitlan</b> ([ten-oak-tee-t\u2019lan], but be lenient)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "This state was the only one of the original thirteen states not to restrict voting by race or gender until 1807, when it restricted the vote to white, property-owning men. The legend of Molly Pitcher originated from a battle in this state, which names the William Paterson-proposed small state plan for the legislature at the Constitutional Convention. Johann Rall was killed after George Washington crossed the Delaware River into, for the point, what state where the Battle of Trenton was fought?", "answer": "<b> New Jersey</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Carl Batecchi wrote about his experiences as one of these people in a Dustoff helicopter unit during the Vietnam War. After his experiences in Biafra, one of these people named Bernard Kouchner founded an international group of them that won the 1999 Nobel Peace Prize. Fictional examples of these people named BJ Hunnicut and Hawkeye Pierce worked in the 4077th during the Korean War in the T.V. show <em>M*A*S*H</em>. For the point, name these professionals who work \u201cwithout Borders\u201d in warzones to heal the wounded.", "answer": "<b> doctor</b>s (accept<b> surgeon</b>s,<b> nurse</b>s,<b> medic</b>s, and anything else related to<b> medicine</b>, especially in war)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This country arrested Peng Ming-min, who spent four years under house arrest before fleeing to Sweden. A leader of this country once declared \u201cthe sky is not big enough for two suns.\u201d This country was the site of the February 28 incident, which resulted in 40 years of martial law called the White Terror. In 1996, this country held its first direct presidential election, resulting in a Kuomintang victory. Chiang Kai-Shek fled to, for the point, what island, home to the Republic of China?", "answer": "<b> Taiwan</b> (accept<b> Republic of China</b> before it is read; do not accept or prompt on People\u2019s Republic of China; do not accept or prompt on China)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The deliverer of this speech was praised as a \u201ca high-flying jet star\u201d by political commentator Chris Matthews for his flashy jet landing. This speech, given aboard the<em> USS Abraham Lincoln</em>, announced that\u201cour allies [had] prevailed\u201d and that \u201cmajor combat operations\u201d had ended. This speech earned its name from a phrase emblazoned across a red, white, and blue banner in the background. For the point, name this widely mocked speech, given by George W. Bush, that prematurely declared success in the Iraq War in 2003.", "answer": "<b> Mission Accomplished</b> speech (prompt on descriptive answers related to George W. Bush declaring victory in the Iraq War in 2003)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Participants in these events would make offerings to the minor deity Taraxippus. The quadriga was often used in these events, one of which instigated a civil disturbance between factions nicknamed the Blues and the Greens. The Nika Riots were spurred by controversy surrounding these events, which were held in Constantinople\u2019s Hippodrome. The Circus Maximus in Rome hosted, for the point, what events in which ancient competitors completed laps in horse-drawn vehicles?", "answer": "<b> chariot race</b>s (prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This city\u2019s artificial Northerly Island was created as part of a namesake \u201cPlan\u201d for this city developed by Daniel Burnham. A series of canal locks developed in this city during the late 19th century reversed the flow of its namesake river. Four red stars are located between two light blue horizontal bars on this American city\u2019s flag. This county seat of Cook County contains the \u201cL\u201d rapid transit system and Navy Pier. For the point, name this most populous city in Illinois.", "answer": "<b> Chicago</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "The rooster was sacred to this empire\u2019s founder because he used an arrow with the point of a cock\u2019s spur to slay his archrival at the Battle of Kirina. This empire was founded by Sundiata and its lands were later ruled by the Songhai Empire. A man whose extravagant hajj devalued gold throughout North Africa ruled this empire in the 14th century. For the point, name this empire, once led by Mansa Musa, which shares its name with a modern west African country.", "answer": "<b> Mali</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}